<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: speaking | Aidan Ryan]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.aidanjryan.com/blog/categories/speaking/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.aidanjryan.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-17T18:02:32-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.aidanjryan.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aidan Ryan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Modern Apps Live! Looking back, looking forward]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.aidanjryan.com/blog/2014/02/05/modern-apps-live-orlando-2013/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-05T15:34:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.aidanjryan.com/blog/2014/02/05/modern-apps-live-orlando-2013</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I presented at the <a href="http://modernappslive.com">Modern Apps Live!</a> conference in Orlando this past November. The whole show was a smashing success. It was an incredible opportunity to connect with peers and colleages, taking a step back to think about the "big picture" of where application development is headed. The next show will be in Las Vegas on March 10-14. I'll be presenting on building a Modern HTML5 "smart client" application. Use my <a href="http://bit.ly/LSPK38Reg">registration link</a> for a $500 savings!<!--more--></p>

<h2>From backend to user experience</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.magenic.com">Magenic</a> has created a unique conference experience where the sessions build on one another to tell the whole story of building a modern application from start to finish. The common thread that ties the sessions together is the creation of a single application platform (a polling app called "MyVote") delivered on diverse clients: Web, iOS, Android, Windows 8 (WinRT), and Windows Phone. The backend is all Azure - SQL and a Web API Cloud Service. The entire development effort was distributed, using Git on Visual Studio Online.</p>

<p>The Magenic team who delivers the conference talks are the same folks who developed the apps. All of the talks emphasize the architecture/design perspective: choosing the right components and patterns for reliable, predictable, successful dlivery. The conference program begins with sessions focused on solution architecture and the backend, follows with development of the various clients, user experience design, and touches on process and tooling around distributed development. We also do a deep-dive workshop on the last day where we dig into the actual nuts and bolts of implementation.</p>

<h2>My talk: HTML5/JavaScript application development</h2>

<p>My talk is about the development of an HTML5 "smart client" app. It is a Single Page App (SPA) developed with AngularJS, TypeScript, and Razor. I describe the benefits of taking an app the web, selection of a JavaScript application framework, architecture of the app components, testing, and cross-cutting concerns. I am really excited about this combination of technologies: AngularJS provides an "opinionated" framework that is very discoverable, and the combination of TypeScript and Razor templating allows us to extend the type-safety of .NET out into the client.</p>

<h2>Next time...</h2>

<p>We're bringing the show to Vegas on March 10-14. We've added some features to the apps, and updated them to keep pace with advancements in their various platforms. Hope to see you <a href="http://modernappslive.com">there</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Silicon Valley Code Camp 2013 - Responsive Re-Engineering]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.aidanjryan.com/blog/2013/10/12/silicon-valley-code-camp-2013-responsive-re-engineering/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-12T10:34:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.aidanjryan.com/blog/2013/10/12/silicon-valley-code-camp-2013-responsive-re-engineering</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spoke at <a href="http://www.siliconvalley-codecamp.com/">Silicon Valley Code Camp</a> on October 5th. The title of my talk was "Responsive Re-Engineering," and it focused on adapting desktop-only web sites to be mobile friendly. I want to thank the organizers and all of the folks who attended the talk. If any of you are reading this and you'd like to talk more about Responsive Web Design, <a href="http://twitter.com/ajryan">get in touch</a>! It was a great experience: lots of great questions and an awesome venue. The <a href="https://github.com/ajryan/CodeCamp2013">code samples</a> and <a href="https://www.slideshare.net/AidanRyan2/responsive-reengineering">slides</a> are online.<!--more--></p>

<p>If your company does ASP.NET development and you are interested in learning how to leverage Responsive Web Design, I would be happy to bring my show on the road. Email me: aidanr (at) magenic.com.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
